# **DOTUN OLAOYE**

14630 Garrett Ave, Apt 614. Apple Valley. Minnesota. 55124 Phone: 507-649-1840 | Email: <a href="mailto:dotun.olaoye@syngenta.com">dotun.olaoye@syngenta.com</a>; <a href="mailto:dotun.olaoye@syngenta.com">olaoyedotun@gmail.com</a> <a href="mailto:https://scholar.google.com/citations?view\_op=list\_works&hl=en&hl=en&user=pTIBop0AAAAJ">https://scholar.google.com/citations?view\_op=list\_works&hl=en&hl=en&user=pTIBop0AAAAJ</a>

#### **SUMMARY**

A solution driven scientist with more than 3 years of professional experience in disease trait discovery and evaluation within the academic, international research institute and industry setting. I combine skills in plant breeding, genetics/genomics, pathology and data analytics in delivering results to achieve goals towards food security.

### **EDUCATION**

Master of Science – Plant Breeding, Genetics and Pathology. University of Arkansas, Fayetteville. USA

May 2021

**♣** *Bachelor of Agriculture* (Honor's: Crop Protection/Pathology) Federal University of Agriculture, Abeokuta. Nigeria.

2017

## SELECTED AWARD/HONORS

- Society Conference Travel Grant Award (\$350) Annual International Meeting (American Society for Horticultural Science, ASHS), Orlando, Florida. U.S.A
- ↓ Two times Graduate School Travel Grant Award (\$600) Annual International Crop Science Meeting (ASA, CSSA, SSSA), San Antonio, Texas. U.S.A

   2019; Annual International Meeting (American Society for Horticultural Science, ASHS) 2020
- Plant Health and Quality Summer School Scholarship (€1200) Campus Vegetal of Angers, Universite Angers, France
  24/06/2019 12/07/2019

2019

# LABORATORY/BENCH SKILLS

Microscopic investigation, serial dilution, isolation and purification of pathogens; (bacteria, fungi, virus and nematodes), maintenance of pathogen isolate/culture, Mycotoxin (Aflatoxin and Fumonisin) extraction and quantification, ELISA, Nucleic Acid (DNA and RNA) extraction and purification, Spectrophotometry, PCR, Gel electrophoresis,

#### FIELD/GREENHOUSE/LABORATORY EXPERIENCE

- ♣ Production of high-quality inoculum for disease assays including those for soybean and snap bean
- ♣ Experience conducting disease assays and phenotyping for resistance to major diseases of field corn, sweetcorn, soybean and snap bean in the field and greenhouse within Syngenta.
- Standardization of disease assay protocols
- Experience with crop (soybean, maize, hemp, spinach, cowpea, common bean and arugula) breeding efforts in the greenhouse/field.
- ♣ Phenotypic (disease) data collection and analysis

- Genetic analysis (marker-trait association analysis) including QTL mapping and genomic prediction
- **♣** Report writing on funded projects

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE (within Syngenta)

- ♣ Experience with planning and implementation of pathology research trials on field corn within Trait Assessment, North America. Syngenta
- Contributes to disease trait evaluation efforts on field corn, sweetcorn, soybean and snap bean for product advancement within Syngenta
- **♣** Moderate user of **SPIRIT** platform within Syngenta
- ♣ Experience with the adoption of **data collection tool (EZCapture)** for research trials within Syngenta
- Familiar with sourcing and managing seed materials via MINT platform within Syngenta
- **♣** Experience with **Benchling** platform for trial record keeping purposes
- ♣ Serves as member on **Market Segment Teams** for Field Corn pathology traits in North America.
- ♣ Provide support/technical expertise for teams (Crop Protection) on pathology efforts.
- ♣ Work in compliance with HSE and/or stewardship policies of the company

#### WORK/RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

♣ Pathology Research Specialist: Pathology Unit. Trait Assessment, North America. Syngenta

May 2021 - Present

- Program Technician: Vegetable Breeding and Genetic Laboratory. Department of Horticulture.
   University of Arkansas, Fayetteville. Arkansas. USA.

  April 2021 May 2021
- Graduate Research Assistant: Spinach breeding and genetics for downy mildew resistance. University of Arkansas, Fayetteville. Arkansas. USA.
  January 2019 April 2021
- **Laboratory Assistant:** (Plant Pathology unit under Dr. Ortega-Beltran Alejandro) International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, IITA-CGIAR. Ibadan. Nigeria. **November 2018 18<sup>th</sup> January 2019**
- **♣** *Graduate Research Unpaid Internship*: (Plant Pathology Laboratory under Dr. Ortega-Beltran Alejandro), **International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, IITA**. Ibadan. Nigeria. **June 2018 November 2018**
- ♣ Undergraduate Research Assistantship: Breeding and Evaluation of Tomato genotypes against Fusarium Wilt British Research Council (DfID)-funded investigated by my undergraduate thesis advisor,

  June 2015 October 2016

#### **JOURNAL PUBLICATION** (or in preparation)

- First author: Association analysis of resistance to the downy mildew pathogen race 5 in spinach worldwide germplasm (manuscript under preparation for journal submission to Frontiers in Plant Science)
- First author: Resistance characterization to races of the downy mildew pathogen of spinach (manuscript under preparation for journal submission to *Euphytica*)
- **First author:** Transcript and proteome profiling for drought tolerance in common bean (manuscript under preparation for journal submission to *Horticulture Research*)

- ♣ MS Thesis: Olaoye, D. (2021). Resistance Screening and Association Mapping for Resistance to the Downy Mildew Pathogen of Spinach. Graduate Theses and Dissertations Retrieved from <a href="https://scholarworks.uark.edu/etd/4107">https://scholarworks.uark.edu/etd/4107</a>
- ♣ Bhattarai, G., D. Olaoye, B. Mou, J. C. Correll, A. Shi. 2022. Mapping and selection of downy mildew resistance locus RPF3 in spinach by low coverage whole genome sequencing. Front. Plant Sci. (under review).
- ↓ Zia, B, A. Shi, D. Olaoye, H. Xiong, W. Ravelombola, P. Gepts, H.F. Schwartz, M.A. Brick, K. Otto, B. Ogg, and S, Chen. 2022. Genome-wide association study and genomic prediction for bacterial wilt resistance in common bean (*Phaseolus vulgaris*) core collection. *Front. Genet*. 
  <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2022.853114">https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2022.853114</a>
- ♣ Ravelombola, W., Shi, A., Huynh, B.L., Qin, J., Xiong, H., Manley, A., Dong, L., Olaoye, D., Bhattarai, G., Zia, B. and Alshaya, H., 2022. Genetic architecture of salt tolerance in a Multi-Parent Advanced Generation Inter-Cross (MAGIC) cowpea population. *BMC genomics*, 23(1), pp.1-22.
- ♣ Ravelombola, W., Dong, L., Barickman, T.C., Xiong, H., Olaoye, D., Bhattarai, G., Zia, B., Alshaya, H., Alatawi, I. and Shi, A., 2021. Evaluation of salt tolerance in cowpea at seedling stage. *Euphytica*, 217(6), pp.1-20.
- Ravelombola, W., Shi, A., Chen, S., Xiong, H., Yang, Y., Cui, Q., Olaoye, D. and Mou, B., (2020). Evaluation of cowpea for drought tolerance at seedling stage. *Euphytica*, 216(8), pp.1-19.
- 4 Yang, Y., Shi, D., Wang, Y., Zhang, L., Chen, X., Yang, X. ... & Yang, G. (2020). Transcript profiling for regulation of sweet potato skin color in Sushu8 and its mutant Zhengshu20. *Plant Physiology and Biochemistry*, 148, 1-9.

# CONFERENCE ARTICLES/PRESENTATION

- ♣ *Presenter:* Olaoye, D., Bhattarai, G., Feng, C., Correll, J. C., & Shi, A. (2020, August). Evaluation of Resistance to *Pfs* race 5 in Worldwide Spinach Collection. In 2020 ASHS Annual Conference. ASHS.
- ♣ Presenter: Olaoye, D., Shi, A., Ravelombola, W. S., Bhattarai, G., & Xiong, H. (2020, August). Drought Tolerance Characterization in two Contrasting Common Bean Genotypes. In 2020 ASHS Annual Conference. ASHS.
- ♣ Presenter: Olaoye, D., Bhattarai, G., Feng, C., Shi, A., & Correll, J. (2019, November). Evaluation of Incomplete Dominance in a Spinach Downy Mildew Resistance Locus. In ASA, CSSA and SSSA International Annual Meetings (2019). ASA-CSSA-SSSA.
- ♣ Co-author Yang, Y., Cui, Q., Qin, J., Ravelombola, W., Bhattarai, G., Zia, B., ... & Shi, A. (2019, November). Evaluation of Drought Tolerance in Common Bean at Seedling Stage. In ASA, CSSA and SSSA International Annual Meetings (2019). ASA, CSSA, and SSSA.
- **♣** Co-author Effect of Exogenous Application of Plant Growth Regulator in the Control of Fusarium oxysporum. F. sp. lycopersici using two Tomato Genotypes International conference of the Biotechnology Society of Nigeria, 2018

**↓** *Co-author* - CAPS Marker *TAO1* and Endonuclease *FOK1* in the Selection of Tomato Genotypes with Homozygous *I2* Resistance Gene to *Fusarium* Wilt - International conference of the Biotechnology Society of Nigeria, 2018

# WORKSHOP/TRAINING ATTENDED

- **5**th Annual Meeting of the Arkansas Bioinformatics Consortium (AR-BIC 2019) Bioinformatics in Food and Agriculture UAMS, Little Rock, AR **February 25 26, 2019**
- ♣ Molecular biology workshop, Inqaba Biotec West Africa, University of Ibadan.

  April 2018

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE AND MEMBERSHIP

- Former Graduate student member: American Society of Horticultural Science; American Society of Agronomy; Crop Science Society of America; Soil Science Society of America
- Adhoc reviewer: Agrosystems, Geosciences & Environment; Nigerian Journal of Biotechnology
- **Provided preliminary reviews** (as a graduate student lab member with Dr. Jim Correll Editor-in-Chief) on three papers for the journal, *Crop Protection*.
- **♣** Provided reviews on three articles (Nigerian Journal of Biotechnology)
- Served as Ad-hoc Secretary for the Vigna spp USDA's CGC at the Annual international Crop Science Meeting held at Texas, USA.
  11/12/19
- Mentored a bachelor's student on manuscript preparation and publication (See comment in acknowledgement section via this link <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/03235408.2020.1715756">https://doi.org/10.1080/03235408.2020.1715756</a>

# GENOMIC/STATISTICAL ANALYTICAL PROFICIENCY

- Experience working with sequence data
- ♣ Moderate skills in bioinformatics/genomic tools and database mining

  Tools includes: R, Python, SAS, JMP, GATK Packages, JOINMAP, QTL analytical softwares, sequence analytical software/tools (TASSEL, MEGA, FARMCPU, GAPIT & BLINK), genomic selection models implemented in R.

## SELECTED LEADERSHIP ROLE/VOLUNTEERING

- ↓ Judge Agronomy and Horticulture 4-H program. University of Minnesota.

   July, 2022
- ♣ Member and volunteer, African Student Organization, University of Arkansas, Fayetteville. U.S.A 2019-21
- **↓** Volunteer member, Volunteer Action Center, Fayetteville, Arkansas 2019 2021

# REFEREES

Available upon request